Guide to the Jacob Berman Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Jacob Berman papers
1863-1975
1920-1939
MS 2014
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
.42
2 boxes
Berman, Jacob, 1878-1974
Abramsky, Yeḥezkel, 1886-1976
Amiel, Moshe Avigdor, 1882-1945
Aronson, Solomon, 1862-1935
Berman, Miriam
Bichovski, Harcha
Brody, Heinrich, 1868-1942
Epstein, Moses Mordecai, 1866-1933
Feinzilber, Š
Grodzinski, Ḥayyim Ozer, 1863-1940
Herzog, Isaac, 1888-1959
Kabak, Aaron Abraham, 1880-1944
Kasovsky, Chayim Yehoshua, 1873-1960
Klein, Samuel, 1886-1940
Kook, Abraham Isaac, 1865-1935
Meltzer, Isser Zalman, 1870-1953
Nissenbaum, Yitzchak, 1868-1942
Reines, Isaac Jacob, 1839-1915
Rosen, Joseph, 1858-1936
Rubinstein, Isaac, 1880-1945
Salanter, Israel, 1810-1883
Shapira, Avraham Duber Kahana, 1870-1943
Soloveichik, Ḥayyim, 1853-1918
Tchernowitz, Chaim, 1870-1949
Tchernowitz, Hadassah
Wertheim, Joseph
Zirelson, Judah Leib, -1941
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged according to document type, and alphabetically thereafter.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Judaica Collection Curator, 2015.
Berman, Jacob, 1878-1974
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - Individuals
      - Abramsky, Yeḥezkel, 1886-1976, 1932, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Amiel, Moshe Avigdor, 1882-1945, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Aronson, Solomon, 1862-1935, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Atlas, Meir, 1923-1924 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Berman, Jacob, 1878-1974, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Berman, Shprintze, 1847-1929, [1921?] (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Bichovski, Harcha, Circa 1920s, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Blum, A. E., 1926 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Brody, Heinrich, 1868-1942, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Epstein, Moses Mordecai, 1866-1933, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Fajans, David, 1860-1935, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Feinzilber, Š., 1929, 1933, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Grodzinski, Ḥayyim Ozer, 1863-1940, 1914, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Herzog, Isaac, 1888-1959, 1937, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Kabak, Aaron Abraham, 1880-1944, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Klein, Samuel, 1886-1940, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Kook, Abraham Isaac, 1865-1935, Circa 1920-1930 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Levi, Hayim, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Lipschuetz, Eliezer Meir, 1921? (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Meltzer, Isser Zalman, 1870-1953, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Nissenbaum, Yitzchak, 1868-1942, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Reines, Isaac Jacob, 1839-1915, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Rosen, Joseph, 1858-1936, 1927-1936 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Rubinstein, Isaac, 1880-1945, circa 1910-1920 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Salanter, Israel, 1810-1883, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Shapira, Avraham Duber Kahana, 1870-1943, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Soloveichik, Ḥayyim, 1853-1918, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Steinberg, Dr. J., 1929 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Tchernowitz, Chaim, 1870-1949 and Tchernowitz, Hadassah, 1908, 1921-1922, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - Wertheim, Joseph, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - Zirelson, Judah Leib, -1941, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Unidentified correspondent, 1918, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Organizations
      - Bet ha-Midrash ha-Gadol ha-Gr"a (Great Synagogue "HaGro"), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Hitachdut Rabonim, Palestine, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Mizrachi Organization World Central, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - United Berdichewer Relief, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - Yeshivat Hevron, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Photographs
    - Berman with girls from Mizrachi school, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Berman with David Ben Gurion, Circa 1935-1955 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Religious Pedagogical Institute article and photo, 1950? (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Berman with Chief Rabbi Ouziel, Circa 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Berman at Israel Prize ceremony, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Moreshet Yaakov, Circa 1975 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Cemetery with Berman's tombstone, Circa 1975 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Receipts and envelopes, Circa 1920-1955 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Wallet sewn from the parchment of a Torah scroll destroyed in a pogrom, Circa 1917 (Box 2)